Welcome to Angularidades, where
we will be talking about topics
around the Angular development
framework to create web applications.
Hi, in today's episode we are joined by Antonio
from Tegucigalpa and Ricardo from San Pedro Sula,
both from Honduras, and we are here in a Creator
Studio Pod inside the convention dedicated
to Google Cloud Next 2026. What do you think of the
space? Amazing, couldn't be better. Yes, we have
a great setup for this episode. Yes, we have
a teleprompter down here, so we will be
guiding ourselves from time to time so as not to lose
the rhythm of the questions. We have to try to do it in
supposedly 20 minutes. So let's see how
we can go through the whole process. And since
we are at an event that revolves around everything
related to cloud computing,
we are going to be talking here today about how to
run Angular applications in hybrid mode,
how to avoid breaking the application, of course,
on the server and how to face that problem of
paralysis that can normally come
to many of us about going to one side with the
managed abstraction of Firebase App Hosting or
going with a very precise, very granular control with
Google Cloud Run. Let's start by giving
a little more context to the topic that for
years the Angular ecosystem was dominated
by CSR, that is, by Client-Side Rendering, and yet
with the recent stabilization, with the
versions fundamentally after Angular
17, they managed to stabilize everything that has to
do with SSR, with incremental hydration,
we already have a series of powerful tools
that allow us to take the load from the client side
towards the server and use the
static mechanisms also with which the web
was used to working since the 90s
with Static Site Generation and well, finally
the code that always lived on the browser side
today can also run on the server.
But, how would you face from the point
of view of technical leadership the decision to move
towards Server-Side Rendering your application,
even if the business side application does not have
a need to have a strong presence
on the side of the search engines, that is,
as it doesn't need to target SEO well, but somehow
to get some advantage from
SSR. What would be the main motivation from
the technical point of view? I think we can't just
look at it just because it's trendy, but that
obviously we have to see other variables and other
factors and one of them is obviously the
performance that we can have. Yes, because many
developers or many companies don't look at
performance that much, they simply see that obviously
the work is being done on the server and that's
when we want to send all the computing load to the
server and let the server do its work. But
obviously we also have many other benefits
and that's where Core Web Vitals come in with certain
metrics, right?, that are going to improve a lot if
the work is no longer done in the browser because the
main load will pass to the server and we are going to have
obviously many improvements like in the Largest
Contentful Paint. That is a very
important metric for the topic of performance. So
it's a metric that benefits a lot from the
migration to Server-Side Rendering. Exactly. If
for example, as you were saying that it's an
Enterprise application, what we can do is divide, for
example, the section for administrators, the
internal tools. Internal tools
don't need to have good SEO and be discovered,
but they need to run well and run fast
so that we don't have so many tickets of, "Hey,
this thing is slow, I'm trying to send
this form, it never loads, I'm trying
to see this part, it never loads." And also
see that, for example, if in the Enterprise there are
people who work in areas with internet
that is not very good, like in Latin America,
India or some parts with little internet access,
we are going to have those problems if we have it on the
browser side. So, if we already send it
precompiled from the server and only many
parts are pure HTML, that's going to go quite
fast. We're going to reduce the tickets and besides
that our application will flow. Exactly.
Yes. Yes. And if suddenly, for example, we have
to make the decision to go with a service provider
that basically Firebase
App Hosting offers in a very fluid way the
ability to deploy applications on it,
but if we have to make the decision between one
and the other that we had mentioned previously
Cloud Run, what is the narrative from the
technical point of view that you normally
should consider given that obviously Firebase
App Hosting is mounted on top of the entire
Cloud Run architecture. Yes, yes, as you said.
Obviously if it's a layer on top of Cloud Run or
of the Google Cloud architecture, for that point
I would believe that something very valid that we must take
into account. Obviously App Hosting is super fast,
we can do the deploy in a very
fast way, obviously it has many benefits as well,
but the moment the limitations to
be able to continue scaling arrive, that's where
Cloud Run comes into play. Exactly. Yes. And at that moment
where we need much more control,
do other little things there that we can't
do with App Hosting because it's a
much more closed abstraction. So there at that
moment it is analyzed and said, "Okay, let's go
to the next step and that is now Cloud Run."
It is also a cost issue because the costs
are quite different and also of necessity
because there are some things that we have inside
App Hosting, as you told me, which are certain
customizations that we can do, but Cloud
Run allows more flexibility if you already know, that is,
if you already know what specific things you need with
the Load Balancers, what things you need, for example,
with Redis or what other things you are going to put on it,
I think it's better that you use Cloud Run.
So, it all depends on what the architecture
you have in the app is and how big it is. Sure.
Yes. And well, Angular currently supports
modern Angular everything that has to do
with the hybrid architecture of being able to define a
file that is simple to read, to write what is
the way in which one is going to serve the application
in a pre-rendered way using SSG
or dynamic, using the whole load from the side
of the client or using what is coming
from the server with non-destructive hydration
mechanisms. But regardless of the fact that
it's very easy from a user experience point of view
to define what thing is going to be
pre-rendered or loaded from the server side
or the client side, what is the foundation that
is behind it when making the decision to
go for any of these three variants and take the
Angular application in a way that can be
efficient so that they use the best of each of
those worlds. Yes, I think that's a
fairly normal pattern and it's one of the best patterns
when saying not only choose just one
path, but you can we can do a mix or
mix two paths. For example, when we have
super static content that is not going to change,
which is the same since it's in local and the
build is done until it's in production,
it never changes. A, to give an example, a
blog post. That blog post will be the same at
all times. So that's a starting point
so that we can use Static Site Generation with
Angular. Correct. Yes. Then we can go to
other pages that might have something a bit more
dynamic and there we can use Server-Side Rendering
when we need to change user data, something
that comes a bit more dynamic. And then the client part,
if we want to process some
data on the client, we have to have access,
obviously to the browser APIs, maybe to
storage and things like that. At that moment, well, yes it is
like each of the paths to follow for what
type of rendering to choose at a given
moment, but while it's true, well, the first
two can be combined and obviously make a
great team. Exactly. Yes, I agree with that. It's
mostly the need of our final user
and the experience that we are giving them.
And in fact, related to the final
experience, also the experience of us
developers matters. And for example, one of
the things that one of the technical problems that
one faces at the time of deploying applications
with Server-Side Rendering is where really and how
should the critical path be of the whole
debugging process of being able to debug an application,
because console logs and client-side
errors that trigger JavaScript problems
are no longer necessarily visible, in fact they are
not when there is a server-side problem,
how is it that you cohesively handle
the transmission, the trace that is being generated
from the servers towards the problems that
could occur in the client or vice versa? Yes,
0:010:00.360,0:10:04.920
we have to change the mentality a little bit, right?
Because we can no longer just double click and open
0:010:04.920,0:10:10.440
the console or developer tools, but
now we have to think of something more like a
0:010:10.440,0:10:14.720
distributed system where there are several streams,
so to speak. Obviously we always have the
0:010:14.720,0:10:18.960
browser, which is what the final user sees.
Also we have the backend part, which can
0:010:18.960,0:10:24.680
be, for example, Node.js possibly external apps
that we are using in our application.
0:010:25.320,0:10:28.480
So, the errors are no longer
in the browser. If something fails,
0:010:28.480,0:10:33.680
it's not in the browser. Obviously it is done
in Google Cloud Logging or in the Google Cloud
0:010:33.680,0:10:39.120
Trace to track the errors. Eh, but what happens
there is that we lose the context a bit,
0:010:39.120,0:10:45.080
right? If while it is true, obviously the
final user says, "There was an error, but how
0:010:45.080,0:10:50.280
do we how do we track it? How do we know where
that error came from?" Because it can be the same browser,
0:010:50.280,0:10:54.360
it can be that an error happens in a request,
it can be that an error happens in the backend,
0:010:54.360,0:10:58.440
there are many places where it can happen and we don't
know clearly. So there we have to start
0:010:58.440,0:11:04.320
to use certain tools and a slightly simple
strategy or a common strategy could be
0:010:04.320,0:11:10.560
that each of the requests can have an ID or
an identical ID for the requests that
0:010:10.560,0:11:15.200
are related, for example. We can use
something that Angular has, which is a transfer state
0:010:15.200,0:11:20.280
in combination with the Google Cloud Trace, the
Google Cloud Logging, to be able to track and give
0:010:20.280,0:11:26.320
a little more context to each of those requests
that might be happening and there know where it is
0:010:26.320,0:11:30.840
that the error is coming from and we are not lost
in the context of knowing, ah, okay, an error happened,
0:010:30.840,0:11:37.680
but we don't know where it comes from. Exactly. Yes, yes,
usually it is using a trace which is a
0:011:37.680,0:11:42.800
trace ID in which one can debug from the
console because we are no longer seeing console
0:011:42.800,0:11:48.800
logs, we are no longer debugging, we are tracing
what things are happening and what processes are the
0:011:48.800,0:11:54.600
ones that are not working well and from there
we can come and repair, build and make better
0:011:54.600,0:12:01.200
solutions. Exactly. And generally in the world of
today, when one uses a generative intelligence
0:012:01.200,0:12:08.040
artificial model to go develop the foundations,
an Angular application with server-side
0:012:08.040,0:12:17.120
rendering, sometimes it can be that if we don't have
our model, our agents well trained,
0:012:17.120,0:12:25.000
it can generate elements that assume direct access
to the DOM, to the browser document,
0:012:25.000,0:12:31.320
for example, it can be window. or it can be to
contexts that are not available in Node.js on the
0:012:31.320,0:12:39.720
side of the server. What is the most direct way,
even the most efficient of being able to train and of
0:012:39.720,0:12:46.840
being able to help these intelligence models
artificial that use the both the documentation
0:012:46.840,0:12:55.160
of Angular as well as the knowledge that this
application is going to run on hybrid platforms
0:012:55.160,0:13:00.960
that do not necessarily depend on the typical
traditional browser-side platform?
0:013:01.720,0:13:07.600
The subject changes quite a bit there too because
we normally write code because
0:013:07.600,0:13:11.800
it is going to execute in the browser, right? The code
is written for that and sometimes the LLMs write
0:013:11.800,0:13:16.760
code that is going to execute in the browser and
can have access to certain APIs that are out there
0:013:16.760,0:13:22.360
and exist. When we start to write code
that is going to execute on the server,
0:013:22.360,0:13:27.720
we are going to start to see like small parts
can start to break of the application,
0:013:27.720,0:13:35.960
we are not only talking about LLMs. So,
we must write or have the LLM write code that
0:013:35.960,0:13:41.680
is safe for the backend. But for that too,
besides adding other tools with this
0:013:41.680,0:13:46.000
new stuff coming out of Angular Skill
and with the MCP, with all these things, also
0:013:46.000,0:13:51.960
we have to give a bit more context to the LLM and
tell it, "Okay, I want you to write code that is
0:013:51.960,0:13:57.480
safe for SSR, not simply just
for the browser." And that from my experience
0:013:57.480,0:14:02.880
helps a lot so that the code is safe for
the browser, to use, for example, in Angular
0:014:02.880,0:14:08.480
the popular Platform Browser to execute code
that it only needs in the browser or use
0:014:08.480,0:14:13.520
some hooks of the components also to
know in what moment to make use of that code,
0:014:13.520,0:14:18.200
trigger certain functions, access certain APIs
that will be available only when the
0:014:18.200,0:14:24.080
app has hydrated, has rendered
completely in the browser. A detail that we
0:014:24.080,0:14:30.480
have to tell the LLM not to use, which
is for example local storage, because we are not
0:014:30.480,0:14:36.720
using local storage on the server. So
yes there are other mechanisms to be able to persist the
0:014:36.720,0:14:42.960
session or somehow being able to use other type
of elements that we don't have time to cover today,
0:014:42.960,0:14:47.280
but yes, right? That it can have access, but
that it does it at the moment it should do it,
0:014:47.280,0:14:51.400
right? Because obviously always the APIs of
even in server rendering we are going to have
0:014:51.400,0:14:56.200
at some point to use the browser APIs,
right? Because the application might require it,
0:014:56.200,0:15:00.960
but do it at the ideal moment, right? After it
is already rendered, that everything is loaded
0:015:00.960,0:15:05.360
in the browser. There now yes we are going to load
some browser API. We can even
0:015:05.360,0:15:10.640
access local storage to, I don't know, save something
or whatever. Minimally, obviously, because the
0:015:10.640,0:15:14.920
app is already made on the server. Obviously
we can use other mechanisms, save it
0:015:14.920,0:15:20.480
in other places too. So, in that way
we will have an application that is safe on the
0:015:20.480,0:15:26.680
server and that doesn't start to fail, obviously.
Sure. And also in the part of the planning
0:015:26.680,0:15:31.600
of the application before writing even the
first line of code, everything that has to do
0:015:31.600,0:15:37.120
with Spec Driven Development, with being able to
pass the necessary instructions so that it has
0:015:37.120,0:15:43.720
a much more precise context. How generally
do you recommend it to be done? Generally it is defining
0:015:43.720,0:15:49.320
well the architecture, what part we are going to start
to use, in what way, what is going to be static,
0:015:49.320,0:15:55.920
what is going to be generated on the server, what things
are dynamic, that we need to be
0:015:55.920,0:16:03.880
on the client and besides that go defining well
what the target goal is at the end. Sure, hey,
0:016:03.880,0:16:09.440
I want this part here to be faster so
that users can move to the next funnel,
0:016:09.440,0:16:15.440
for example, hey, if I have an application in which
I want people to log in, I mean,
0:016:15.440,0:16:22.800
I need the login to go fast or that the first
SPA it has, that something is seen, that it doesn't leave
0:016:22.800,0:16:27.560
the page blank, that we have that infinite
loading loop that makes people say,
0:016:27.560,0:16:31.880
"This thing doesn't work, it's broken and I'm leaving." And
there one is going to look for all the shortcuts and in a certain
0:016:31.880,0:16:36.720
way being able to have that direct conversation with
the AI to be able to comment on it regardless of
0:016:36.720,0:16:43.960
if we are using Antigravity or any other
integrated development environment and start giving
0:016:43.960,0:16:51.520
shape to the application before the application
even has its draft structure. Yes.
0:016:51.520,0:16:57.520
So, thank you very much again for being
here in Las Vegas at Google Cloud Next 2026,
0:016:57.520,0:17:01.960
right? Thank you very much for the invitation.
It's always a pleasure to talk about these
0:017:01.960,0:17:07.080
type of tools and technologies and even more here
in the Google Cloud Next with this beautiful setup
0:017:07.080,0:17:12.000
that I'm not going to stop admiring, right? Because
it's super top notch for what we are doing,
0:017:12.000,0:17:19.280
so I feel quite pro here,
right? Well, see you soon then and
0:017:19.280,0:17:27.160
stay tuned for new episodes.
Bye. Thanks for listening to this podcast and
0:017:27.160,0:17:32.320
I hope the topics discussed during the
episode are useful to you. If you haven't subscribed yet,
0:017:32.320,0:17:36.760
I invite you to do so so as not to miss any of
the future topics related to frontend,
0:017:36.760,0:17:43.880
graphical interfaces, software architecture
and web development through Angular.